I'd like to tell you about two games of chess.
أود أن أروي لكم عن مباريتين في الشطرنج.
The first happened in 1997, in which Garry Kasparov,
الأولى حدثت عام 1997 حيثُ خسر غاري كاسباروف
a human, lost to Deep Blue, a machine.
الإنسان أمام ديب بلو - آلة.
To many, this was the dawn of a new era,
بالنسبة للكثيرين، كان هذا بمثابة فجر لعهد جديد،
one where man would be dominated by machine.
حيث تسيطر الآلة على الإنسان.
But here we are, 20 years on, and the greatest change
ولكن هانحن ، بعد 20 عاما ،وأعظم تغيير
in how we relate to computers is the iPad,
من حيث إرتباطنا بأجهزة الكمبيوتر هو الــ آي باد،
not HAL.
وليس هال.
The second game was a freestyle chess tournament
كانت اللعبة الثانية مباراة حرة للشطرنج
in 2005, in which man and machine could enter together
عام 2005 حيث استطاع الإنسان والآلة المشاركة سويا
as partners, rather than adversaries, if they so chose.
كشركاء عوضا عن خصوم -إن اختاروا ذلك.
At first, the results were predictable.
في البداية، كانت النتائج متوقعة.
Even a supercomputer was beaten by a grandmaster
حتى الحاسوب العملاق تعرض للهزيمة من قبل الخبير الكبير
with a relatively weak laptop.
الذي كان معه جهاز محمول ضعيف نسبياً.
The surprise came at the end. Who won?
المفاجئة كانت في النهاية. من فاز؟
Not a grandmaster with a supercomputer,
ليس الخبير الكبير ومعه الحاسوب العملاق،
but actually two American amateurs
ولكن في الواقع هاويان أمريكيان
using three relatively weak laptops.
يستخدمان ثلاثة أجهزة محمولة ضعيفة نسبيا.
Their ability to coach and manipulate their computers
قدرتهما على التدريب ومعالجة أجهزتهما
to deeply explore specific positions
لاستكشاف متعمق لمواضع معينة
effectively counteracted the superior chess knowledge
تصدت بفعالية للمعرفة المتفوقة للشطرنج
of the grandmasters and the superior computational power
للخبراء الكبار والقوة الحاسوبية المتفوقة
of other adversaries.
لخصوم الآخرين.
This is an astonishing result: average men,
هذه نتيجة مدهشة : رجل عادي
average machines beating the best man, the best machine.
وأجهزة عادية يغلبون أفضل رجل، أفضل جهاز.
And anyways, isn't it supposed to be man versus machine?
وعلى أي حال، أليس من المفترض أن يكون الرجل ضد الجهاز؟
Instead, it's about cooperation, and the right type of cooperation.
عوضاً عن ذلك، فالأمر عبارة عن تعاون ،نوع صحيح من التعاون.
We've been paying a lot of attention to Marvin Minsky's
كنا نعطي الكثير من الاهتمام إلى رؤية مارفن منسكي
vision for artificial intelligence over the last 50 years.
للذكاء الاصطناعي على مدى الـ 50 سنة الماضية.
It's a sexy vision, for sure. Many have embraced it.
إنها رؤية مثيرة بالطبع. تبناها الكثيرون.
It's become the dominant school of thought in computer science.
أصبحت مدرسة الفكر المسيطرة في علوم الحاسب.
But as we enter the era of big data, of network systems,
ولكن مع دخولنا عصر البيانات الكبيرة و أنظمة الشبكات ،
of open platforms, and embedded technology,
والمنصات المفتوحة والتكنولوجيا المضمنة،
I'd like to suggest it's time to reevaluate an alternative vision
أود اقتراح أنه حان الوقت لإعادة تقييم رؤية بديلة
that was actually developed around the same time.
والتي في الواقع طُورَت في الوقت نفسه تقريبا.
I'm talking about J.C.R. Licklider's human-computer symbiosis,
إني أتحدث عن رؤية جوزيف كارل روبنت ليكليدر لتعايش الإنسان مع الكمبيوتر،
perhaps better termed "intelligence augmentation," I.A.
والتي يطلق عليها "زيادة الذكاء"،
Licklider was a computer science titan who had a profound
كان ليكليدر خبيرا في علوم الحاسب وكان لديه
effect on the development of technology and the Internet.
أثر عميق على تطور التكنولوجيا والإنترنت.
His vision was to enable man and machine to cooperate
رؤيته كانت لتمكين الإنسان والآلة من التعاون
in making decisions, controlling complex situations
في صنع القرارات والتحكم في المواقف المعقدة
without the inflexible dependence
من دون الاعتماد غير المرن
on predetermined programs.
على البرامج المحددة مسبقا.
Note that word "cooperate."
لاحظوا كلمة "تعاون."
Licklider encourages us not to take a toaster
يشجعنا ليكليدر ألا نأخذ محمصة
and make it Data from "Star Trek,"
ونجعلها بيانات من "ستار تريك"
but to take a human and make her more capable.
ولكن أن نأخذ إنسانا ونجعله أكثر كفاءة.
Humans are so amazing -- how we think,
البشر مذهلون جداً - طريقة تفكيرنا،
our non-linear approaches, our creativity,
ونهجنا غير الخطّي ، وإبداعنا،
iterative hypotheses, all very difficult if possible at all
والفرضيات المتكررة، جميعها صعبة إن لم تكن مستحيلة التنفيذ
for computers to do.
على أجهزة الكمبيوتر.
Licklider intuitively realized this, contemplating humans
لاحظ ليكليدر ذلك بشكل حدسي، البشر المتفكرون
setting the goals, formulating the hypotheses,
يحددون الأهداف ويصيغون الفرضيات،
determining the criteria, and performing the evaluation.
ويحددون المعايير ويجرون التقييم.
Of course, in other ways, humans are so limited.
بالطبع البشر قدراتهم محدودة ، من نواحي أخرى.
We're terrible at scale, computation and volume.
نحن سيئون في القياس والحساب والأحجام.
We require high-end talent management
نتطلب إدارة مواهب متطورة
to keep the rock band together and playing.
لمتابعة سير العمل.
Licklider foresaw computers doing all the routinizable work
تنبأ ليكليدر بأن أجهزة الحاسب تستطيع عمل جميع الأعمال الروتينية
that was required to prepare the way for insights and decision making.
المطلوبة لإعداد الطريق للأفكار وصناعة القرارات.
Silently, without much fanfare,
بهدوء، ودون ضجة إعلامية،
this approach has been compiling victories beyond chess.
استطاع هذا النهج حصد انتصارات عديدة أبعد من لعبة الشطرنج.
Protein folding, a topic that shares the incredible expansiveness of chess —
عملية طي البروتين -موضوع يشارك لعبة الشطرنج التوسعية المذهلة
there are more ways of folding a protein than there are atoms in the universe.
هنالك طرق لطي البروتين أكثرمن عدد الذرات المتواجدة في الكون.
This is a world-changing problem with huge implications
هذه مشكلة مغيرة للعالم ذات تداعيات ضخمة
for our ability to understand and treat disease.
على قدرتنا على فهم ومعالجة الأمراض.
And for this task, supercomputer field brute force simply isn't enough.
ولهذه المهمة، القوة الغاشمة لمجال الحاسوب العملاق ببساطة لا تكفي
Foldit, a game created by computer scientists,
"فولدت" ،هي لعبة صنعها علماء الحاسب،
illustrates the value of the approach.
توضح قيمة هذا النهج.
Non-technical, non-biologist amateurs play a video game
هواة غير تقنيين ولا متخصصين في البيولوجيا يلعبون لعبة فيديو
in which they visually rearrange the structure of the protein,
حيث يعيدون بصرياً ترتيب بنية البروتين،
allowing the computer to manage the atomic forces
والسماح للحاسب بإدارة القوات الذرية
and interactions and identify structural issues.
والتفاعلات وتحديد المسائل الهيكلية.
This approach beat supercomputers 50 percent of the time
هذا النهج تغلب على الحاسوب العملاق بنسبة 50% من الوقت
and tied 30 percent of the time.
وتعادل بنسبة 30% من الوقت.
Foldit recently made a notable and major scientific discovery
فولدت اكتشفت حديثا اكتشافا بارزا ومهما
by deciphering the structure of the Mason-Pfizer monkey virus.
عن طريق فك رموز هيكل فيروس القردة ميسون-فايزر.
A protease that had eluded determination for over 10 years
الأنزيم البروتيني الذي استعصى لأكثر من 10 سنوات
was solved was by three players in a matter of days,
تم حله من قبل ثلاثة لاعبين في غضون عدة أيام،
perhaps the first major scientific advance
قد يكون أول إكتشاف علمي
to come from playing a video game.
يأتي من خلال لعب لعبة فيديو.
Last year, on the site of the Twin Towers,
العام الماضي ،في موقع برجي مركز التجارة العالمي
the 9/11 memorial opened.
أفتتح النصب التذكاري لـ 9/11.
It displays the names of the thousands of victims
يظهر أسماء آلاف الضحايا
using a beautiful concept called "meaningful adjacency."
مستخدما مفهوما جميلا يدعى "الجوار ذا معنى."
It places the names next to each other based on their
يضع الأسماء بجانب بعض بناء على
relationships to one another: friends, families, coworkers.
علاقتهم ببعض: أصدقاء أو عوائل أو زملاء.
When you put it all together, it's quite a computational
عندما نضع كل ذلك مع بعض فهو تحدي حاسوبي كبير:
challenge: 3,500 victims, 1,800 adjacency requests,
3,500 ضحية و 1,800 طلبات جوار
the importance of the overall physical specifications
وأهمية المواصفات الجسدية الشاملة
and the final aesthetics.
والجماليات النهائية.
When first reported by the media, full credit for such a feat
عندما تم إعلان ذلك لأول مرة من قبل وسائل الإعلام، تم إعطاء كامل الفضل لهذا الإنجاز
was given to an algorithm from the New York City
إلى خوارزمية من مدينة نيو يورك
design firm Local Projects. The truth is a bit more nuanced.
من شركة تصميم مشاريع محلية .الحقيقة أكثر تفصيلا من ذلك.
While an algorithm was used to develop the underlying framework,
في حين أنه تم استخدام خوارزمية لوضع الإطار الأساسي،
humans used that framework to design the final result.
استخدم الإنسان ذلك الإطار لتصميم العمل النهائي.
So in this case, a computer had evaluated millions
ففي هذه الحالة، قام الكمبيوتر بتقييم ملايين
of possible layouts, managed a complex relational system,
التخطيطات المحتملة وإدارة نظام ترابطي معقد،
and kept track of a very large set of measurements
ومتابعة مجموعة كبيرة من القياسات
and variables, allowing the humans to focus
والمتغيرات بحيث سمحت للبشر بالتركيز
on design and compositional choices.
على خيارات التصميم والتركيب.
So the more you look around you,
فكلما نظرت حولك
the more you see Licklider's vision everywhere.
كلما رأيت رؤية ليكليدر في كل مكان.
Whether it's augmented reality in your iPhone or GPS in your car,
سواء كانت حقيقة مدمجة في الآي فون الخاص بك أو في نظام الجي بي أس في سيارتك،
human-computer symbiosis is making us more capable.
تعايش الإنسان مع الكمبيوتر تجعلنا أكثر قدرة.
So if you want to improve human-computer symbiosis,
إذا كنت تريد تحسين تعايش الإنسان مع الكمبيوتر،
what can you do?
ماذا يمكنك أن تفعل؟
You can start by designing the human into the process.
تستطيع البدء بإدخال الإنسان بالعملية.
Instead of thinking about what a computer will do to solve the problem,
عوضا عن التفكير بما سيفعله الحاسب لحل المشكلة،
design the solution around what the human will do as well.
صمم الحل حول ما سيفعله الإنسان أيضا.
When you do this, you'll quickly realize that you spent
عندما تفعل ذلك ،ستلاحظ بسرعة أنك أمضيت
all of your time on the interface between man and machine,
كل وقتك على الواجهة بين الإنسان والآلة،
specifically on designing away the friction in the interaction.
وعلى وجه التحديد تصميم البعد عن الاحتكاك في التفاعل.
In fact, this friction is more important than the power
في الواقع، هذا الاحتكاك أكثر أهمية من قوة
of the man or the power of the machine
الإنسان أو قوة الآلة
in determining overall capability.
في تحديد القدرة الإجمالية.
That's why two amateurs with a few laptops
لهذا السبب استطاع اثنان من الهواة مع عدد محدود من الأجهزة المحمولة
handily beat a supercomputer and a grandmaster.
بسهولة أن يغلبوا الحاسوب العملاق والخبير الكبير.
What Kasparov calls process is a byproduct of friction.
ما يدعوه كاسبروف عملية هو نتيجة ثانوية للاحتكاك.
The better the process, the less the friction.
كلما كانت العملية أفضل، كان الاحتكاك أقل.
And minimizing friction turns out to be the decisive variable.
وقد تبين أن تقليل الاحتكاك هو العامل الحاسم.
Or take another example: big data.
أو خذ مثالا آخرا: البيانات الكبيرة.
Every interaction we have in the world is recorded
كل تفاعل موجود في العالم مسجّل
by an ever growing array of sensors: your phone,
من طرف مجموعة مجسات متكاثرة : هاتفك،
your credit card, your computer. The result is big data,
بطاقتك الاتمانية، كمبيوترك. النتيجة هي بيانات كبيرة،
and it actually presents us with an opportunity
وهي بالحقيقة تقدم لنا فرصة
to more deeply understand the human condition.
لفهم دقيق أكثر لوضع الإنسان.
The major emphasis of most approaches to big data
التركيز الأكبر لأغلب التوجهات للبيانات الكبيرة
focus on, "How do I store this data? How do I search
تركز على ، "كيف أخزن هذه البيانات ؟ وكيف أبحث
this data? How do I process this data?"
في هذه البيانات؟ كيف أعالج هذه البيانات؟
These are necessary but insufficient questions.
هذه أسئلة مهمة ولكن غير كافية.
The imperative is not to figure out how to compute,
الضروري ليس أن نعرف كيف نعالج،
but what to compute. How do you impose human intuition
ولكن ماذا تعالج. كيف يمكن أن توظف حدس اللإنسان
on data at this scale?
على بيانات بهذا المستوى؟
Again, we start by designing the human into the process.
مرة أخرى، نبدأ بتوظيف الإنسان داخل العملية.
When PayPal was first starting as a business, their biggest
عندما بدأت شركة "بي بال"، كان أكبر
challenge was not, "How do I send money back and forth online?"
تحدي لديهم ليس "كيف أحول المال عن طريق الانترنت ؟"
It was, "How do I do that without being defrauded by organized crime?"
ولكن " كيف أفعل ذلك من غير احتيال جرائم منظمة؟"
Why so challenging? Because while computers can learn
لماذا يبدو تحديا كبيرا؟ لأن بينما الكمبيوترات قادرة على تعلُم
to detect and identify fraud based on patterns,
اكتشاف و معرفة احتيال مبني على أنماط
they can't learn to do that based on patterns
لاتستطيع تعلم نفس الشيء على أنماط
they've never seen before, and organized crime
لم يسبق لها رؤيتها، والجرائم المنظمة
has a lot in common with this audience: brilliant people,
لها عوامل مشتركة مع الحضورهنا : أناس رائعين
relentlessly resourceful, entrepreneurial spirit — (Laughter) —
لديهم امكانيات قوية و روح ريادة الأعمال -(ضحك)
and one huge and important difference: purpose.
و اختلاف كبير ومهم : الهدف
And so while computers alone can catch all but the cleverest
ولمدة كانت الحواسيب قادرة على اصطياد كل شيء إلا
fraudsters, catching the cleverest is the difference
المحتالين الأكثر ذكاءاً، اصطياد الأذكى هو الاختلاف
between success and failure.
بين النجاح والفشل
There's a whole class of problems like this, ones with
هناك مستوى كامل من مشكلات كهذه، مشكلات مع
adaptive adversaries. They rarely if ever present with a
الخصوم المتكيفين. هم من النادر جداً ان يواجهوا
repeatable pattern that's discernable to computers.
نمط متكرر ملحوظ لأجهزة الكمبيوتر
Instead, there's some inherent component of innovation or disruption,
على العكس، هناك بعض العناصر المتأصلة للابتكار أوالتخريب
and increasingly these problems are buried in big data.
وبشكل متزايد هذه المشكلات تكون مدفونة في بيانات كبيرة
For example, terrorism. Terrorists are always adapting
على سبيل المثال، الارهاب. الارهابيون دائماً يتكيفون
in minor and major ways to new circumstances, and despite
بطرق بسيطة أو كبيرة لظروف مختلفة، وبخلاف
what you might see on TV, these adaptations,
ما تراه على التلفاز، هذه التكيفات
and the detection of them, are fundamentally human.
والقدرة على كشفهم هي بشكل اساسي إنساني.
Computers don't detect novel patterns and new behaviors,
أجهزة الكمبيوتر لا تكتشف أنماط جديدة وسلوكيات جديدة،
but humans do. Humans, using technology, testing hypotheses,
ولكن البشر يفعلون. البشر، باستخدام التكنولوجيا ،اختبار الفرضيات
searching for insight by asking machines to do things for them.
يبحثون عن تبصر من خلال طلبهم من الأجهزة أن تفعل أشياء لهم
Osama bin Laden was not caught by artificial intelligence.
أسامة بن لادن لم يُقبض عليه باستخدام الذكاء الصناعي
He was caught by dedicated, resourceful, brilliant people
بل قبض عليه أناس مخلصين ذوي امكانيات و أذكياء
in partnerships with various technologies.
بالمشاركة مع تكنولوجيات مختلفة.
As appealing as it might sound, you cannot algorithmically
بقدر ماهو مغري، لا تقدر بطريقة خوارزمية
data mine your way to the answer.
أن تستخرج البيانات لتجد الحل
There is no "Find Terrorist" button, and the more data
ليس هناك زر " اعثر على ارهابي" ، وكلما كثرت البيانات
we integrate from a vast variety of sources
التي ندمجها من مصادر كثيرة متنوعة
across a wide variety of data formats from very
خلال أشكال واسعة و مختلفة من أشكال البيانات من
disparate systems, the less effective data mining can be.
من أنظمة مختلفة ، كلما قلت فاعلية تنقيب البيانات.
Instead, people will have to look at data
على العكس، اُناس سوف يتوجب عليهم النظر في البيانات
and search for insight, and as Licklider foresaw long ago,
والبحث عن دلالات ،وكما تنبأ لكليدر منذ مدة طويلة،
the key to great results here is the right type of cooperation,
المفتاح لنتائج باهرة هنا هو النوع الجيد من التعاون،
and as Kasparov realized,
ومثلما أدرك كاسباروف،
that means minimizing friction at the interface.
هذا يعني تخفيف الاحتكاك في الواجهات.
Now this approach makes possible things like combing
الآن هذا التوجه يجعل أمور ممكنة مثل البحث
through all available data from very different sources,
في بيانات المتوفرة من مصادر مختلفة،
identifying key relationships and putting them in one place,
التعرف على علاقات مهمة ووضعها في مكان واحد،
something that's been nearly impossible to do before.
شيء لطالما كان أقرب للمستحيل أن يُفعَل سابقاً.
To some, this has terrifying privacy and civil liberties
للبعض، لهذا الأمر تداعيات مخيفة على الخصوصية و الحريات المدنية.
implications. To others it foretells of an era of greater
بالنسبة للبعض الآخر، فهذا ينبأ بعصر
privacy and civil liberties protections,
حيث تكون الخصوصية و الحريات المدنية محمية بشكل أكبر،
but privacy and civil liberties are of fundamental importance.
ولكن الخصوصية والحريات المدنية أمور ذات أهمية أساسية.
That must be acknowledged, and they can't be swept aside,
هذا الشيء يجب أن يُعترف به ولا يُهمّش،
even with the best of intents.
حتى مع النوايا الجيدة.
So let's explore, through a couple of examples, the impact
إذا دعونا نستكشف، من خلال بعض الأمثلة، الأثر
that technologies built to drive human-computer symbiosis
الذي قامت به التكنولوجيات لدفع التعايش بين الإنسان والحاسوب
have had in recent time.
من وقت قريب.
In October, 2007, U.S. and coalition forces raided
في أكتوبر 2007، داهمت الولايات المتحدة وقوات التحالف
an al Qaeda safe house in the city of Sinjar
البيت الآمن للقاعدة في مدينة سنجار
on the Syrian border of Iraq.
على الحدود السورية للعراق.
They found a treasure trove of documents:
وجدوا كنزا من الوثائق:
700 biographical sketches of foreign fighters.
700 من نسخ لسير ذاتية لمقاتلين أجانب .
These foreign fighters had left their families in the Gulf,
هؤلاء المقاتلون الأجانب قد تركوا عائلاتهم في الخليج
the Levant and North Africa to join al Qaeda in Iraq.
الشام وشمال أفريقيا للالتحاق بالقاعدة في العراق.
These records were human resource forms.
هذه السجلات كانت استمارات موارد بشرية.
The foreign fighters filled them out as they joined the organization.
المقاتلون الأجانب قاموا بتعبئتها عندما انضموا للمنظمة.
It turns out that al Qaeda, too,
تبين أن القاعدة ،أيضاً،
is not without its bureaucracy. (Laughter)
ليست خالية من البيروقراطية. (ضحك)
They answered questions like, "Who recruited you?"
قاموا بالإجابة على أسئلة من قبيل :، "من قام بتوظيفك؟"
"What's your hometown?" "What occupation do you seek?"
"ما هي بلدتك؟" "ماهي المهنة التي تريدها؟"
In that last question, a surprising insight was revealed.
في السؤال الأخير، تم الكشف عن حقيقة مدهشة.
The vast majority of foreign fighters
الأغلبية الساحقة من المقاتلين الأجانب
were seeking to become suicide bombers for martyrdom --
كانوا يريدون أن يصبحوا انتحاريين جهاديين--
hugely important, since between 2003 and 2007, Iraq
والأمر مهم لدرجة كبيرة،بين عامي 2003 و 2007 تعرض
had 1,382 suicide bombings, a major source of instability.
العراق لأزيد من 1328 عملية تفجير انتحاري، وهي أحد العوامل المهمة لعدم الاستقرار هناك.
Analyzing this data was hard. The originals were sheets
تحليل هذه البيانات كان صعبا. فالنسخ الأصلية
of paper in Arabic that had to be scanned and translated.
كانت مكتوبة بالعربية، التي كان علينا تفحصها وترجمتها .
The friction in the process did not allow for meaningful
الاحتكاك في هذه العملية لم يسمح لنا
results in an operational time frame using humans, PDFs
بالوصول لنتائج ذات مغزى في الحيز الزمني العملي، بالاستعانة بالإنسان ، ال PDF
and tenacity alone.
والمثابرة وحدها.
The researchers had to lever up their human minds
بل كان على الباحثين أن يقرنوا عصارة تفكيرهم
with technology to dive deeper, to explore non-obvious
بالتكنولوجيا للغوص بشكل أعمق ، واستكشاف الفرضيات
hypotheses, and in fact, insights emerged.
غير الواضحة، وبالفعل ظهرت مجموعة من الحقائق.
Twenty percent of the foreign fighters were from Libya,
20 في المائة من المقاتلين الأجانب جاؤوا من ليبيا،
50 percent of those from a single town in Libya,
50 في المائة منهم جاؤوا من مدينة واحدة في ليبيا،
hugely important since prior statistics put that figure at
والأمر الهام جدا هنا ، أنه في احصائيات سابقة كان هذا الرقم
three percent. It also helped to hone in on a figure
في حدود 3 في المائة. والفضل راجع في ارتفاع هذا العدد
of rising importance in al Qaeda, Abu Yahya al-Libi,
وتنامي أهمية القاعدة؛ إلى أبو يحيى الليبي ،
a senior cleric in the Libyan Islamic fighting group.
رجل دين بارز في الجماعة الإسلامية المقاتلة الليبية.
In March of 2007, he gave a speech, after which there was
في مارس 2007، ألقى خطابا، ارتفعت بعده
a surge in participation amongst Libyan foreign fighters.
مشاركة الليبيين ضمن المقاتلين الأجانب.
Perhaps most clever of all, though, and least obvious,
ربما يكون الأمر الأكثر ذكاء، وبالمقابل، الأقل بديهية ،
by flipping the data on its head, the researchers were
عن طريق تقليب البيانات رأسا على عقب، أن الباحثين
able to deeply explore the coordination networks in Syria
كانوا قادرين على استكشاف شبكات الربط في سوريا
that were ultimately responsible for receiving and
التي كانت مسؤولة بالنهاية عن استقبال
transporting the foreign fighters to the border.
ونقل المقاتلين الأجانب إلى الحدود.
These were networks of mercenaries, not ideologues,
كانت تلك عبارة عن شبكات مرتزقة و ليست شبكات ايديولجية،
who were in the coordination business for profit.
الذين دخلوا في الخط على أساس العمل من أجل الربح.
For example, they charged Saudi foreign fighters
فكانوا على سبيل المثال، يطلبون مالا من المقاتلين الأجانب السعوديين
substantially more than Libyans, money that would have
أكثر بكثير من الليبيين ،ذلك المال الذي كان
otherwise gone to al Qaeda.
ليذهب للقاعدة إن لم يأخذوه هم.
Perhaps the adversary would disrupt their own network
ربما كان الخصم ليعطلوا شبكاتهم الخاصة
if they knew they cheating would-be jihadists.
لو كانوا يعلمون أن من يخونهم هم من الجهاديين .
In January, 2010, a devastating 7.0 earthquake struck Haiti,
في عام 2010 ، ضرب زلزال مدمر بقوة 7 درجات جزيرة هايتي،
third deadliest earthquake of all time, left one million people,
ثالث أخطر زلزال مميت عرفه التاريخ، خلف مليونا،
10 percent of the population, homeless.
أي 10 في المائة من مجموع سكان البلاد، بلا مأوى.
One seemingly small aspect of the overall relief effort
أحد جوانب الإغاثة التي قد تبدو صغيرة بالنظر إلى المجهود الإغاثي الشامل
became increasingly important as the delivery of food
أصبح يكتسب أهمية متزايدة ، مثل توصيل الطعام
and water started rolling.
وتداول المياه.
January and February are the dry months in Haiti,
يناير و فبراير هما الشهران الأكثر جفافا في هايتي،
yet many of the camps had developed standing water.
ومع ذلك فالعديد من المخيمات كانت بها مياه راكدة.
The only institution with detailed knowledge of Haiti's
المؤسسة الوحيدة التي تملك معلومات مفصلة
floodplains had been leveled
عن سهول هايتي الفيضية، قد دمرت
in the earthquake, leadership inside.
بسبب الزلزال، مع مسؤوليها بداخلها.
So the question is, which camps are at risk,
إذن فالسؤال ، ماهي المخيمات الأكثر عرضة للخطر؟
how many people are in these camps, what's the
كم عدد الأشخاص في هذه المخيمات،
timeline for flooding, and given very limited resources
وماهي مواقيت الفيضانات، وبالنظر إلى الموارد والبنيات المحدودة جدا
and infrastructure, how do we prioritize the relocation?
كيف يمكننا تحديد أولوية نقل السكان؟
The data was incredibly disparate. The U.S. Army had
كانت البيانات متباينة بشكل لا يصدق.وكان الجيش الأمريكي
detailed knowledge for only a small section of the country.
يملك معلومات مفصلة فقط عن جزء صغير من البلاد.
There was data online from a 2006 environmental risk
كانت هناك بيانات على الانترنت من مؤتمر الأخطار
conference, other geospatial data, none of it integrated.
البيئية، بيانات جيو مكانية أخرى، ليست بالمتكاملة.
The human goal here was to identify camps for relocation
كان الهدف الإنساني هنا، أن نحدد أماكن لنقل الناس
based on priority need.
بناء على الاحتياجات ذات الأولوية .
The computer had to integrate a vast amount of geospacial
كان على الحاسوب أن يدمج مجموعات هائلة من المعلومات الجيومكانية
information, social media data and relief organization
معلومات من مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي ،معلومات إغاثية
information to answer this question.
للإجابة عن هذا السؤال.
By implementing a superior process, what was otherwise
من خلال تنفيذ عملية متفوقة، الأمر الذي كان
a task for 40 people over three months became
يتطلب عمل 40 شخصا طوال ثلاثة أشهر
a simple job for three people in 40 hours,
أصبح عملا بسيطا يتطلب ثلاثة أشخاص و 40 ساعة عمل،
all victories for human-computer symbiosis.
مما يعتبر تتويجا للتعاون بين الانسان و الحاسوب.
We're more than 50 years into Licklider's vision
مرت 50 سنة على رؤية ليكليدر
for the future, and the data suggests that we should be
عن المستقبل، والبيانات تقترح أن علينا أن نكون
quite excited about tackling this century's hardest problems,
متحمسين لمعالجة أصعب مشاكل هذا القرن،
man and machine in cooperation together.
بتعاون بين الإنسان و الحاسوب معا.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)